<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Eric Poe]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/tags/api.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T14:43:37-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpoe.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code Like You Need Protection]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/02/14/code-like-you-need-protection"/>
            <updated>2014-02-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/02/14/code-like-you-need-protection</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="background">Background</h2>

<p>I was recently tasked with  programming a connecty-bit between a Google Drive Form and our instance of SolarWinds Web Help Desk. Both are great products. Both offer fabulous APIs.</p>

<p>My overall plan was to periodically grab all information from the default worksheet of the Google Drive Form, translate it to JSON, and submit it to Web Help Desk to generate a ticket for each Google Drive Form record. I realized that I was faced with a dilemma: how do I retain client records in the Google Drive Form and only read from the newest records to generate these tickets?</p>

<p>I first  thought to add a "read" flag to each record that I had read and created a ticket. The problem that I saw with this algorithm was that I would have to read through N records each time I wanted to check for new tickets. If the tickets were in the lower-end of the number spectrum, I would hardly notice the time it took to iterate through all of these tickets; but once the amount of records reaches a "critical mass,"" the read-delay might exceed the period-length between the times the underlying-script checks for new records.</p>

<p>I decided that my best bet would be to create a new worksheet, an "archive" worksheet, and move each record, once processed, from from the default worksheet to this new "archive" worksheet.</p>

<h2 id="how-it%E2%80%99s-done">How it’s done</h2>

<p>My first love, in regards to programming, is PHP, so I thought I might program the  intermediate script in PHP; however, the server I was to run this on did not include PHP. On the other hand, it did run Python 2.</p>

<p>It has been a while since I have coded anything in Python, and even longer since I have written anything in Python 2. So, I fired up my browser and a handy VIM instance and checked out the very worthy <a href="http://learnpythonthehardway.org/book/">Python The Hard Way</a>.</p>

<p>After spending a day on that site, I felt that I was ready to tackle the Python 2 aspects of the Google Drive API ("gdata"). The trick was in figuring out which aspects of the gdata API would grab the data that I needed.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, one of my coworkers found the json API documentation from <a href="http://www.webhelpdesk.com/api/">Stormwinds Web Helpdesk API</a> and provided a proof-of-concept via CURL and some code from the documentation. Once I knew that json would work, I knew that I had to generate json code from the gdata API and submit it to our instance of the Solar Winds Web Helpdesk application via their API and my personal API key.</p>

<p>The rest of the script required that I determine how to generate the originating JSON and how to submit that JSON text via Python2.</p>

<p>The title of this document is something like "code like you need protection." This is in reference to something that I recently (aka "last 6 months") heard that goes something like: code like the next person to read your code is a serial killer who knows where you live. In other words, make sure that the code you write is well structured, well documented, and makes logical sense. To that end, I probably spent more time documenting and refactoring my code so that the 6-months-from-now-me who has to tweak the code doesn’t have to spend an inordinate amount of time trying to figure out what my present-me was attempting to do.</p>

<p>The final script can be seen in my <a href="https://github.com/ericpoe/ask-a-tech">GitHub repository</a>.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>