<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Eric Poe]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/tags/dartlang.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-09T04:18:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpoe.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Decisions, Decisions]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/03/03/Decisions-Decisions"/>
            <updated>2014-03-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/03/03/Decisions-Decisions</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am currently feeling a bit of push and pull between at least two different decisions. I have a “when you have time for it” project that I am thinking of building in <a href="http://laravel.com/">Laravel</a>. I am also interested in learning more about the <a href="http://dartlang.org/">Dart language</a> with Dart’s implementation of <a href="https://angulardart.org/">Angular.js</a>.</p>

<p>Ach! Decisions, decisions.</p>

<p>For my study of Laravel, I am reading (and practicing) Dayle Rees’s <a href="https://leanpub.com/codebright">Code Bright</a>. For my study of Dart, I am running haphazard through various online documentation; yet, I am taking notes and posting them to my <a href="https://github.com/ericpoe/codedoc-dart">github account</a>.</p>

<p>My hope is that I will be able to marry the two disparate projects into one franken-product which will satisfy my brain and, to a lesser-extant, my employer.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dart Flight School]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/02/20/Dart-Flight-School"/>
            <updated>2014-02-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2014/02/20/Dart-Flight-School</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This evening, I attended the <a href="https://www.dartlang.org/events/2014/flight-school/">Dart Flight School</a> at the Google Fiber Space in Kansas City.  Dart Flight School is a global event occurring throughout February.</p>

<p>I treated this event as an introduction to the <a href="https://www.dartlang.org/">Dart programming language</a>. I walked in to the event knowing only that Dart was created by Google to be like javascript. What I learned is that Dart is designed to be similar to javascript in that some browsers, like Dartium (a portmanteau of “Dart” and Chromium”) can launch it natively if they have the DartVM; yet for others, for instance all of the currently popular browsers, Dart compiles to a minified javascript.</p>

<p>We looked at a simple text-manipulation application that was very similar to the “<a href="https://www.dartlang.org/codelabs/darrrt/">Darrrt</a>” introduction to the language. We also ran through building a node.js-like web server using Dart. I’ll see if I can find the code from the presenters and will add a link to it to this post.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.dartlang.org/tools/editor/">Dart Editor</a> is based on the Eclipse IDE, but is not as bulky.</p>

<p>Dart is now on my list of programming languages and libraries to learn.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>