<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Eric Poe]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/tags/drupal.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-20T01:16:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpoe.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Playing with Docker and Linked Containers]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2016/01/26/playing-with-docker"/>
            <updated>2016-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2016/01/26/playing-with-docker</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my current job, I am starting the process to upgrade our PHP 5.4 application to a PHP 5.6 application (PHP 7 is not yet support by the majority of the 3rd party libraries we use). I have been tasked with building the staging server for use in testing our legacy application as well as our newer Symfony-based application. We are using an older version of MySQL as well.</p>

<p>At some point, we will want to experiment with PHP 7.x and later versions of MySQL or MariaDB. Yet, will we want to build a brand new server each time?</p>

<p>This seems like a perfect opportunity to play with <a href="http://docker.io">Docker</a>.</p>

<p>I had first looked at Docker a little over a year ago. I had tried to build a dev environment entirely from Docker, but it and I were not yet ready for each other. I could not see Docker as anything other than another way to launch a Vagrant box for development.</p>

<p>This weekend, I looked at Docker again. Now Docker includes a feature called "<a href="https://docs.docker.com/compose/">Docker Compose</a>." This allows one to build a Docker manifest within a YAML file rather than as a complex command-line string.</p>

<p>I played. I looked at building a new Drupal 8 box with a separate MySQL server. As a docker-compose YAML file, this is pretty straight-forward:</p>

<p><code>docker-compose.yml</code></p>

<pre><code class="yaml">drupal8:
  image: drupal
  links:
    - drupal_database:mysql
  ports:
    - 8085:80
drupal_database:
  container_name: drupal_database
  image: mariadb:5.5
  environment:
    MYSQL_ROOT_PASSWORD: examplepass
    MYSQL_USER: user
    MYSQL_PASSWORD: password
    MYSQL_DATABASE: drupal_db
</code></pre>

<p>The above creates two Docker machines: "drupal8" and "drupal_database." The "drupal8" Docker machine is linked to the "drupal_database" which is running MariaDB 5.5. To launch this, I just run <code>docker-compose up</code> from the directory that contains this <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file. This is the equivalent to running:</p>

<pre><code>docker run --name drupal_database \
  -e MYSQL_ROOT_PASSWORD=examplepass \
  -e MYSQL_USER=user \
  -e MYSQL_PASSWORD=password \
  -e MYSQL_DATABASE=drupal_db \
  -d mariadb:5.5

docker run --name drupal8 \
  -p 8085:80 \
  --link drupal_database:mysql \
  -d drupal
</code></pre>

<p>I was able to come up with a working <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file within 30 minutes. It took me much longer to come up with the right <code>docker run</code> statements to make two Docker containers and have the Drupal container link to the MySQL container. Natch, had I read further down the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/drupal/">Docker Hub Drupal page</a>, I would have been given a huge clue as to how to connect the two; I just needed to add the appropriate port. Nonetheless, the YAML is much easier me to configure and update than the two <code>docker run</code> commands are.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>