<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title><![CDATA[Eric Poe]]></title>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/tags/omphaloskepsis.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://ericpoe.com/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-29T22:26:50-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://ericpoe.com/</id>
        <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[Expectation vs Reality: my first 1.5 years of professional programming]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2015/11/29/dev-expectation-vs-dev-reality"/>
            <updated>2015-11-29T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2015/11/29/dev-expectation-vs-dev-reality</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have been a professional developer for over a year and a half now.</p>

<p>About a year ago, my friend and mentor, John Kary, asked me how the job measured up to my expectations. I replied, honestly, that my expectations were met. However, I hadn't given it much thought since I was busy trying to learn so many new things. So, at the time, my expectation was that new developers spend a lot of time learning new things. Expectation: met.</p>

<p>Since that time, I have continued to learn new things, but I have also had time to think about the question more in depth.</p>

<p>I realized that I had many expectations of dev-life while I was studying programming.</p>

<p><strong>Caveat:</strong> Your mileage may vary</p>

<h3 id="expectation-1---programming-is-a-young-man%27s-game">Expectation 1 - Programming is a Young Man's Game</h3>

<p>This was probably my largest fear with changing my career and entering programming as a full-time job. I had read too much about <em>brogramming</em>, sexism, and ageism being rampant in the development world. As a middle-aged dude, I was worried about entering this career that was run by 20-something guys that call each other "bruh."</p>

<h3 id="reality-1---programming-is-open-to-all">Reality 1 - Programming is Open to All</h3>

<p>My first interview for my job was with a female boss and a potential coworker who was older than me and was also female. I have told both of them since that this put my fears to rest and made the rest of the interview-process much easier. My second interview was with the team, which was made up of the female boss, the older-than-me female developer, a younger female developer, a remote guy via robot interface, a younger guy, and my friend, John Kary. Another member of the team was absent due to his grandson being born.</p>

<p>Since that time, we have hired a guy from Pakistan, a slightly younger guy, a slightly older guy, and a much younger guy. I would like to see more women apply for the job openings. Perhaps next time.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-2---programming-requires-uml">Expectation 2 - Programming Requires UML</h3>

<p>My programming classes utilized <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unified_Modeling_Language" title="Unified Modeling Language">UML</a>, the various textbooks and other programming books also utilized UML. So, I imagined that dev meetings utilized UML on a dry-erase board.</p>

<h3 id="reality-2---learning-requires-uml">Reality 2 - Learning Requires UML</h3>

<p>In various team meetings, 1-on-1 dev meetings, and informal discussions, I have yet to see UML be utilized.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-3---developers-have-a-computer-science-degree">Expectation 3 - Developers Have a Computer Science Degree</h3>

<p>I imagined developer discussions being in some meta-language that incorporated algorithms, Big-O notation, and obscure design patterns.</p>

<h3 id="reality-3---developers-come-from-all-walks-of-life">Reality 3 - Developers Come From All Walks of Life</h3>

<p>Perhaps half of my team has some kind of Computer Science background and degree. Other members of my team have backgrounds in varied subjects from construction to film-studies.</p>

<p>In listening the various podcasts and attending various conferences and user-group meetings, I think that there is no fairly typical developer background. One can expect someone with a computer-science degree, but there are plenty of good developers out there without a degree, much less a computer-science degree.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-4---developers-are-invested-in-their-community">Expectation 4 - Developers Are Invested In Their Community</h3>

<p>I was a member of a developer community a decade before I became a professional developer. I have gone to developer conferences in Kansas City and Dallas and have met with many developers from those communities. I expected that all developers were interested in meeting with and working with developers from their community outside of their 9-to-5 job.</p>

<h3 id="reality-4---developers-come-from-all-walks-of-life">Reality 4 - Developers Come From All Walks of Life</h3>

<p>I know that this is the same as &#35;3; however, it fits here, too.</p>

<p>I have also met plenty of developers whom I have tried to recruit to join a local user group, yet they gave a non-committal "I'll look into it" when pressed. Most developers whom I have met are interested in programming for the 40-hours a week they are contracted to program. Outside of that time, they are interested in pursuing their own interests: wood-working, beer brewing, robot fighting, knitting, parade-float building, running, &amp; etc.</p>

<p>Even for me, family is my number 1 priority. Yet, I devote time to organizing a PHP User Group, planning and mentoring a <a href="http://coderdojokc.com/">CoderDojo</a>, and studying programming concepts and technologies outside of work.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-5---if-you-don%27t-play-reindeer-games%2C-you-don%27t-belong">Expectation 5 - If You Don't Play Reindeer Games, You Don't Belong</h3>

<p>What I knew of programmers is what I knew from media and my nerd friends. <a href="https://cardsagainsthumanity.com/">Cards Against Humanity</a>, Dungeons and Dragons, comic books, video games, Star Wars/Trek, and pop-culture ephemera rule developer society.</p>

<h3 id="reality-5---developers-come-from-all-walks-of-life">Reality 5 - Developers Come From All Walks of Life</h3>

<p>Guess what? Developer !== Dork. You might know some developers who fall into that stereotype, but you probably know others who have interests outside of developer stereotypes.</p>

<p>I have yet to play Cards Against Humanity at work. Yet, I have played it once after a CoderDojo session. I have had several Star Wars/Trek discussions with coworkers, but not all coworkers.</p>

<p>At lunch, we mostly talk about family and recent events in our lives. I have recently started a dev book club with my team for a once-per-week lunch discussion. Some of us gather once per month for <a href="http://nomadphp.com">NomadPHP</a> with a follow-up discussion.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-6---memes-are-huge">Expectation 6 - Memes Are Huge</h3>

<p>Before I got my job, I started reading <a href="https://reddit.com">reddit</a>. One thing that I learned is that memes are huge. So I ran through a bunch of memes on <a href="http://memegenerator.net/">meme generator</a>.</p>

<h3 id="reality-6---memes-are-huge-for-some">Reality 6 - Memes Are Huge for Some</h3>

<p>Memes are memes because they are memes. That's tautology for you.</p>

<p>Memes are drawn from popular culture. So, when I was a kid, saying "This is not the assignment you're looking for" was utilizing a meme. We just didn't call it that. 15 years ago, saying to a friend, "Wassup!" was utilizing a meme. We just didn't call it that.</p>

<p>So now, with the easy usage of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emoji">emoji</a> and the <a href="https://bitbucket.org/atlassianlabs/ac-koa-hipchat-sassy"><code>/meme</code></a> command in HipChat, memes are all too easy to utilize in a textual discussion.</p>

<p>Yet, not all of us know what the heck some of these memes mean. And some don't even bother with using memes in textual discussion. Memes tend to be a shibboleth in a team when a team shouldn't require such watch-words or phrases.</p>

<h3 id="expectation-7---programmers-are-a-monoculture">Expectation 7 - Programmers are a Monoculture</h3>

<p>When attending a conference, it's easy to see that the vast majority of attendees are younger white guys. The lines to the men's room are long whereas the lines to the ladies' room are non-existant. All programmers are heavy into nerd-core and oontz-oontz electronic music.</p>

<h3 id="reality-7-%26-conclusion---developers-come-from-all-walks-of-life">Reality 7 &amp; Conclusion - Developers Come From All Walks of Life</h3>

<p>This, I think, is the ultimate expectation. All of the expectations above reflect this expectation.</p>

<p>When I was a CS student, classmates were from various genders, sexual orientations, ethnic backgrounds, races, and religions. This expectation was already smashed.</p>

<p>When I joined the league of professional programmers, I met programmers from all walks of life: programmers who grew up dirt poor and programmers who grew up with plenty; programmers who grew up steeped in nerd-core and programmers who came about it quite accidentally.</p>

<p>I am a middle-aged white guy. Yet, I've only been in this game professionally for 1.5 years. I have a lifetime of experience behind me in jobs &amp; a career other than programming. You could take a glance at me and think that I am the very model of a modern career programmer. Yet, you could not be more wrong.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
            <entry>
            <title type="html"><![CDATA[My Year of Code]]></title>
            <link href="http://ericpoe.com/blog/2015/11/13/my-year-of-code"/>
            <updated>2015-11-13T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
            <id>http://ericpoe.com/blog/2015/11/13/my-year-of-code</id>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>2015 was my year to really dive into PHP. Up until this year, PHP was  hobby language for me -- much as Python, Haskell, C++, Dart, JavaScript, and Java have been hobby languages. Granted, last year I finally took a job where PHP is where I spend half of my time.</p>

<p>This year, I took up intensive study of PHP. At the beginning of the year, I poured over the <a href="http://www.phparch.com/books/zend-php-5-certification-study-guide-3rd-edition/">Zend PHP 5 Certification Study Guide, Third Edition</a> by Davey Shafik and Ben Ramsey. I even passed the <a href="http://www.zend.com/en/services/certification/php-5-certification">Zend Certified PHP Engineer exam</a> and earned my <a href="http://www.zend.com/en/yellow-pages/ZEND027285">Zend Certification</a>. I also took up more of a leadership role in my local PHP user group, <a href="http://www.meetup.com/kcphpug/">KCPHPUG</a>, gave a few talks, and have been hosting meetups both at work and at a local café. In the late Spring/early Summer, I began work on a PHP library called <a href="https://github.com/ericpoe/ophp">OPHP</a>. In April, I attended the <a href="http://lonestarphp.com/">Lone Star PHP conference</a> and got to meet and hang out with quite a few luminaries of the community.</p>

<p>I think I can safely say that 2015 has been a year of PHP for me.</p>

<p>For next year, my language of intensive study will be JavaScript. No matter who I talk with about programming, JavaScript seems to be the <em>lingua franca</em> of web programming. I have already started to look deeply into Sencha's <a href="https://www.sencha.com/products/extjs">Ext JS</a>, which is the JavaScript framework we use at work. <a href="http://es6-features.org/">EcmaScript 6</a> has piqued my interest since it was ratified in June. I have also been interested in learning more about <a href="https://nodejs.org">node</a> since it has usage in <a href="http://electron.atom.io/">Atom Electron</a> and beyond.</p>

<p>By this time next year, I hope to have a native comfort in JavaScript.</p>
]]></content>
        </entry>
    </feed>